<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Hugo on Ibrahim Ahmed</title>
    <link>http://iahmed.me/tags/hugo/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Hugo on Ibrahim Ahmed</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Ibrahim Ahmed</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 30 Apr 2018 02:51:16 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://iahmed.me/tags/hugo/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Hugo and Jupyter Notebooks</title>
      <link>http://iahmed.me/post/2018-04-30-hugo-jupyter/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Apr 2018 02:51:16 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://iahmed.me/post/2018-04-30-hugo-jupyter/</guid>
      <description>[Hugo][1] is a static site generator. It takes a bunch of markdown files and renders them to HTML. It is fast and simple.
[Jupyter Notebooks][2] are an interactive front-end for python (with support for other languages too). They execute code, display its output, and render markdown all in a browser window. The notebooks are a neat compilation of formatted code and text generated as HTML.
I use Hugo for my site.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trials and Tribulations of Maintaining a Hugo Blog</title>
      <link>http://iahmed.me/post/2017-09-30-maintaining-a-hugo-blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Sep 2017 17:29:58 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://iahmed.me/post/2017-09-30-maintaining-a-hugo-blog/</guid>
      <description>As of the writing of this post, I maintain this site using my very own theme created in hugo. Hugo is a static site generator. It takes a bunch of plain text, applies a theme, and renders it as HTML. This is opposed to applications like Wordpress that assemble a page each time its served, to put it simply. This compute once, use many times approach saves on processing time and makes a site more portable.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Optimizing static sites with hugo</title>
      <link>http://iahmed.me/post/2017-02-06-optimizing-static-sites-with-hugo/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2017 10:07:58 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://iahmed.me/post/2017-02-06-optimizing-static-sites-with-hugo/</guid>
      <description>According to httparchive the average size of a web page in 2016 was around 2.5MB. Now this may not seem a lot in this age where the internet is the primary media delivery platform - but it is worth noting that most web pages serve text as their primary content. Looking at the report sheds light on what constitutes an average web page:
The HTML content takes up around 50-60kB. Images, understandably, make up the biggest chunk with ~1.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>