<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Engineering on Ibrahim Ahmed</title>
    <link>http://iahmed.me/categories/engineering/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Engineering on Ibrahim Ahmed</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Ibrahim Ahmed</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2017 23:19:08 -0600</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://iahmed.me/categories/engineering/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>A Poor Man&#39;s Introduction to Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>http://iahmed.me/post/poor-mans-reinforcement-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2017 23:19:08 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://iahmed.me/post/poor-mans-reinforcement-learning/</guid>
      <description>Reinforcement Learning (RL) is one of the many ways to implement artificial intelligence (AI). AI is the design of &amp;ldquo;intelligent&amp;rdquo; agents that maximize their chances of success at some goal. The goal can belong to any problem: from winning a game of tic-tac-toe, to recognizing speech, to steering a car.
A problem can be approached in many different ways. An agent can search for all possible options and choose the best.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Algorithms: Balancing</title>
      <link>http://iahmed.me/post/algorithm-concepts/algorithms-balancing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2017 18:47:26 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://iahmed.me/post/algorithm-concepts/algorithms-balancing/</guid>
      <description>Balancing in algorithms refers to minimizing the complexity of an algorithm by making sure that its constituent parts share the load efficiently. It is not a technique for solving problems. Instead it helps us understand how an existing solution may be optimized.
The theory of balancing Say there is a problem of size \(n\). The problem is such that it can be broken down into a sequence of smaller problems.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A case study in choosing algorithms</title>
      <link>http://iahmed.me/post/2016-08-13-a-case-study-in-choosing-algorithms/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Aug 2016 03:29:23 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://iahmed.me/post/2016-08-13-a-case-study-in-choosing-algorithms/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This past year, I have been crunching data from &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/hazrmard/DarkMatterHalos&#34;&gt;dark matter simulations&lt;/a&gt;. Data size can get pretty large when it comes to scientific computing. As I write this post, I have a script running on 3.8 TB (that&amp;#8217;s right &amp;#8211; 3,700 gigabytes) of cosmic particles. At these levels one starts thinking about parallelizing computations. And therein lay my dilemma and a soon to be learned lesson.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Talking With Satellites</title>
      <link>http://iahmed.me/post/2015-10-14-talking-with-satellites/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Oct 2015 19:16:21 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://iahmed.me/post/2015-10-14-talking-with-satellites/</guid>
      <description>This year I am leading a senior design team in developing a software defined radio that can talk with a satellite that Vanderbilt just launched. Compared to a normal radio, an SDR has most of the signal processing functions implemented virtually. This means that it can change its operation on the fly. An interesting application of SDRs is cognitive radio: that is, radios communicating with other radios in their vicinity and adjusting their frequencies to maximize their use of the bandwidth.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>