<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gravity on Ibrahim Ahmed</title>
    <link>http://iahmed.me/tags/gravity/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Gravity on Ibrahim Ahmed</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Ibrahim Ahmed</copyright>
    <atom:link href="http://iahmed.me/tags/gravity/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational Slingshots</title>
      <link>http://iahmed.me/post/GravitationalSlingshots/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Jan 2017 10:48:32 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://iahmed.me/post/GravitationalSlingshots/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: This article was originally published on
&lt;a href=&#34;astroibrahim.wordpress.com&#34;&gt;astroibrahim&lt;/a&gt; on Apr 10, 2013.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I always wondered why doesn’t the sun slow space probes down when
they are leaving the Earth for outer planets. Isn’t there a risk
that the probe might change its trajectory and fall into the sun?
There is. You see, the more distant the space probe gets from the
Sun, the more potential energy it gains. However, energy must be
conserved at all costs. Therefore the probe loses its Kinetic
energy (and therefore its speed) in order to get away from the
sun. It is the same as when you throw a rock up into the air.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there comes a point, as with the rock, when the probe loses
all of its kinetic energy. At that time it has reached as far
away from the sun as it can. Yes, you could add thrusters to make
sure the probe continues its journey. But the extra weight and
inefficiency of propellants known to us make it an unsuitable
alternative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter the Gravitational Slingshot! Nature’s way of compensating
us (very marginally) for all the millions of years we’ve been
dragged through the mud in the name of evolution. Through this
method, space probes go into a partial orbit around a planet and
emerge on the other side with a greater velocity. “No!”, some
might say, because it is a violation of conservation of energy.
Intuitively it seems that way, but it is all a matter of
relativity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;http://iahmed.me/img/posts/slingshot.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine there is a probe approaching a planet with a velocity
‘u’. To an observer on the planet, the apparent velocity of the
probe’s approach will be ‘V+u’, where ‘V’ is the planet’s and ‘u’
is the probe’s heliocentric velocity, i.e. velocity relative to
the Sun. It will go into orbit at that speed. Now, when it comes
out of orbit on the other side, it is still moving with a
velocity ‘V+u’ relative to the planet’s surface. But the planet
is also moving in the same direction at velocity ‘V’. So the
final velocity as the probe leaves orbit will be ‘V+(V+u)’. Of
course, some of that velocity will be reduced due to the planet’s
potential, but in the end it will still be greater than the
probe’s initial velocity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you look at what happened overall, ignoring how it happened,
the probe approaches a moving planet at a certain velocity and
“bounces off” at a higher velocity. It is just like when you
throw a ball at the face of a moving train, the ball bounces off
at a higher velocity. Now, the ball changes its momentum (first
going in one direction, then another) and transfers that change
to the train to ensure conservation. But the train is
comparatively so massive that we do not notice the minuscule
change in its velocity. That’s the same with planets and probes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The effective increment in the probe’s velocity is due to the
orbited body’s velocity relative to the Sun (analogously, the
change in velocity of the rebounding ball depends on the train’s
relative velocity to the ground). Of course, the Sun’s velocity
relative to itself is zero. Therefore ‘V’ will be zero. So there
will be no gravitational slingshot from the Sun (towards planets
in its orbit) even though it is the most massive body in the
solar system; just like there will be no increment in the
velocity of the ball when you throw it at the ground.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>