<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Quantum Mechanics on Ibrahim Ahmed</title>
    <link>http://iahmed.me/tags/quantum-mechanics/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Quantum Mechanics on Ibrahim Ahmed</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Ibrahim Ahmed</copyright>
    <atom:link href="http://iahmed.me/tags/quantum-mechanics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Is cold the new hot?</title>
      <link>http://iahmed.me/post/is_cold_the_new_hot/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Jan 2017 11:00:25 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://iahmed.me/post/is_cold_the_new_hot/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: This article was originally published on
&lt;a href=&#34;astroibrahim.wordpress.com&#34;&gt;astroibrahim&lt;/a&gt; on April 17, 2013.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few days back, a friend shared an
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nature.com/news/quantum-gas-goes-below-absolute-zero-1.12146&#34;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; with me. It talked of
how scientists had managed to achieve temperatures below absolute
zero. Does it mean that temperature has to be redefined? Has our
understanding of thermodynamics been flawed for the past hundred
years. No, it turns out. It is all a matter of semantics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Absolute Zero. This is the temperature at which a particle has
the minimum possible energy. The energy is NOT zero because that
would violate the Heisenberg uncertainty principle (that you
cannot know the energy and its duration with absolute certainty).
However that zero-state energy is a quantum quantity, so for all
intents and purposes, the particle itself appears stationary.
Classically, it is impossible to go below absolute zero because
for all the matter that we know of, it will never have negative
energy (because the zero state energy prevents energy from going
past zero and into the negative).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore when you talk of temperatures below absolute zero, and
you know that there is nothing wrong with absolute zero, then
logically there must be something going on with “Temperature”.
The layperson will call temperature the hotness of something.
Some one more well versed in science will call it the average
kinetic energy of the particles. All of these definitions are
correct in the same way Newton’s gravity is correct i.e. it works
for our observations. But in order to really understand
temperature, you need to understand entropy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Entropy in a sense is the amount of disorder in a system. Imagine
making a mound of sand on a table. Now shake the table. The sand
particles will spread out as they roll down from the mound.
Because the particles are now spread out, the entropy of the
system has increased. The farther a particle is from the original
position of the mound, the more effectively it has harnessed the
energy you gave the system by vibrating the table. If the table
was infinitely expansive, the particles would continue spreading
out and absorbing the energy you provide and increasing the
entropy of the system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a system with infinite states, energy and disorder have a
positive relationship.
In a system with infinite states, energy and disorder have a
positive relationship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;http://iahmed.me/img/posts/temp_infinite.png&#34;&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;In a system with infinite states, energy and
    disorder have a positive relationship.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is temperature, the ratio of energy required to the change
in entropy. The greater the energy required for the same increase
in entropy, the greater will be the temperature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is a catch: what if you provide more energy to the
system but the disorder (entropy) decreases instead. Is it
possible to shake the table and make the sand particles more
ordered? If it is, then that would mean that the temperature of
the system is negative because the change in energy is positive,
but the change in entropy is negative, so the ratio (which
represents temperature) is negative. Imagine that the table is
not infinite. Instead it has little walls on the edges. As you
shake the table, the sand particles start to spread out (they
gain energy, and increase entropy). The temperature increases.
But there comes a point when they reach the edges. Then they
start to accumulate again. The more you shake the table, the
greater is the particle accumulation on the edges. At that point,
an increase in energy of the system is in fact decreasing its
disorder. Thus the temperature has become negative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a system with finite states, energy and disorder develop a
negative relationship.
In a system with finite states, energy and disorder develop a
negative relationship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;http://iahmed.me/img/posts/temp_finite.png&#34;&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;In a system with finite states, energy and  
    disorder develop a negative relationship.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is exactly what the scientists mentioned in the article did.
They trapped the molecules using lasers and magnetic fields, so
that after absorbing certain amount of energy, the barriers
created by the magnetic fields and lasers would cause particles
to accumulate around the same energies. In the classical sense,
the particles were hotter because they had a greater energy, but
since the disorder in the system was lessened, their temperature
was negative i.e. below absolute zero.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>