<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Matlab on Ibrahim Ahmed</title>
    <link>http://iahmed.me/tags/matlab/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Matlab on Ibrahim Ahmed</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Ibrahim Ahmed</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 24 Sep 2018 14:17:46 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://iahmed.me/tags/matlab/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Modern control: State space equations</title>
      <link>http://iahmed.me/post/ai-methods-for-control-systems/4-modern-state-space-equations/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Sep 2018 14:17:46 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://iahmed.me/post/ai-methods-for-control-systems/4-modern-state-space-equations/</guid>
      <description>In modern control approaches, systems are analyzed in time domain as a set of differential equations. Higher order differential equations are decomposed into sets of first order equations of state variables that represent the system internally. This produces three sets of variables:
 Input variables are stimuli given to the system. Denoted by $u$. Output variables are the result of the current system state and inputs. Denoted by $y$. State variables represent the internal state of a system which may be obscured in the output variables.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Classical control: Transfer functions</title>
      <link>http://iahmed.me/post/ai-methods-for-control-systems/3-classical-transfer/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Sep 2018 15:17:40 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://iahmed.me/post/ai-methods-for-control-systems/3-classical-transfer/</guid>
      <description>A transfer function relates the output of a system to its input when it is represented in the Laplace domain. An assumption is made that initial steady-state response is 0. If $Y(s)$ is the output of a system, $X(s)$ is the input, then the transfer function is:
$$ H(s) = \frac{Y(s)}{X(s)} $$
Example - A Car    A car as a system: The input is the acceleration. The output is the total distance travelled.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Control Systems: Overview</title>
      <link>http://iahmed.me/post/ai-methods-for-control-systems/1-control-systems/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Sep 2018 11:34:21 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://iahmed.me/post/ai-methods-for-control-systems/1-control-systems/</guid>
      <description>Overview of control theory A control system is a mechanism that dictates the behaviour of another system. A controller relies on signals it can measure to estimate performance of the system. In response it sends out signals that influence the system towards the desired state.
A controller is designed by modelling a system as a set of differential equations in time. By analysing that model, a control strategy can be developed.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>